<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="rss.xsl"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
    <channel>
        <title>Eldiron Blog</title>
        <link>https://eldiron.com/blog</link>
        <description>Eldiron Blog</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Wed, 16 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Eldiron v0.8.50 Released]]></title>
            <link>https://eldiron.com/blog/2025/07/16/eldiron-v0.8.50</link>
            <guid>https://eldiron.com/blog/2025/07/16/eldiron-v0.8.50</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 16 Jul 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Eldiron v0.8.50 Released]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="eldiron-v0850-released">Eldiron v0.8.50 Released<a href="https://eldiron.com/blog/2025/07/16/eldiron-v0.8.50#eldiron-v0850-released" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Eldiron v0.8.50 Released" title="Direct link to Eldiron v0.8.50 Released">​</a></h2>
<p>After I was mostly working on the graphical aspects of Eldiron in the last releases, this release focuses on the core gameplay mechanics.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="new-features">New Features<a href="https://eldiron.com/blog/2025/07/16/eldiron-v0.8.50#new-features" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to New Features" title="Direct link to New Features">​</a></h2>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="server">Server<a href="https://eldiron.com/blog/2025/07/16/eldiron-v0.8.50#server" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Server" title="Direct link to Server">​</a></h3>
<ul>
<li>New 'entered' and 'left' entity system events when entering / leaving named sectors.</li>
<li>New 'teleport' command which either takes one argument (destination sector name in the same region) or two, the destination sector name and the name of the destination region (which will transfer the character to a different region). The entity will be transferred to the center of the destination sector.</li>
<li>New <code>[light]</code> data attributes to enable light emission for entities and items.</li>
<li>New 'set_emit_light(True / False)` cmd to enable / disable light emission for an entity or an item.</li>
<li>New special <code>active</code> item attribute which specifies if the item is active or not. On startup (or if the attribute is changed) a new <code>active</code> event is send to the item which can than decide what to do based on the value, like enabling / disabling light emission for a torch.</li>
<li>New <code>intent</code> system. Define the current player intent (like "talk", "use", "open" etc.) via the new <code>intent</code> parameter for button widgets. Server will send new <code>intent</code> events to both entities and items for direction based and click based item interations.</li>
<li>New <code>health</code> config attribute which holds the name of the default entity health attribute, by default <code>HP</code>.</li>
<li>New <code>mode</code> entity attribute which holds the current state string of the entity. Set to <code>active</code> on entity instantiation and <code>dead</code> when the health attribute is smaller or equal to 0.</li>
<li>New <code>death</code> event send to an entity when the health attribute is smaller or equal to 0.</li>
<li>New <code>id</code> command which returns the id of the current entity.</li>
<li>New <code>took_damage</code> command (my_id, from_id, damage_amount). This command sends out messages and checks for death.</li>
<li>New <code>goto</code> command (sector name, speed). Makes an NPC go to a sector. Sends <code>arrived</code> event on arrival with the name of the sector as value.</li>
<li>New  <code>close_in</code> command (target id, target radius, speed). Makes an NPC close in (in weapon range given by the target radius) of the entity id with the given speed. Once the target is in range a <code>closed_in</code> event is send.</li>
<li>New <code>kill</code> event send to the attacker when he kills his target. The value of the event is the id of the dead target.</li>
</ul>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="client">Client<a href="https://eldiron.com/blog/2025/07/16/eldiron-v0.8.50#client" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Client" title="Direct link to Client">​</a></h3>
<ul>
<li>New <code>intent</code> command to invoke an intention via key shortcuts (same as actions).</li>
</ul>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="creator">Creator<a href="https://eldiron.com/blog/2025/07/16/eldiron-v0.8.50#creator" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Creator" title="Direct link to Creator">​</a></h3>
<ul>
<li>Tileset tool: Preview icons now in the minimap.</li>
<li>Tilepicker: Icons preview on hover in the minimap.</li>
</ul>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="bug-fixes">Bug Fixes<a href="https://eldiron.com/blog/2025/07/16/eldiron-v0.8.50#bug-fixes" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Bug Fixes" title="Direct link to Bug Fixes">​</a></h2>
<ul>
<li>Make game widgets honor the global render graph.</li>
<li>Info viewer did not show item values correctly.</li>
<li>Changed <code>Data</code> tool shortcut from <code>A</code> to <code>D</code>.</li>
<li>When adding tiles to the project the background renderer was not updated correctly.</li>
<li>Adjust Undo / Redo state when switching regions.</li>
</ul>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="documentation">Documentation<a href="https://eldiron.com/blog/2025/07/16/eldiron-v0.8.50#documentation" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Documentation" title="Direct link to Documentation">​</a></h2>
<ul>
<li>Cleaned up and refactored the reference section of the documentation of Eldiron.com.</li>
<li>Wrote documentation in the reference for all new features and changes.</li>
</ul>
<hr>
<p>The plan is to finish the remaining missing core gameplay mechanics in the next 1-2 releases (and feature them in the Hideout 2D example), implement the node based behavior system and after that focus on a 3D Dungeon crawler example. Than we are not too far away from version 1!</p>
<p>I will create a new video showcasing all the new features soon, so don't forget to check and subscribe to the YouTube channel!</p>
<p>Take care,
Markus</p>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>releases</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[New Video | Rigging]]></title>
            <link>https://eldiron.com/blog/2025/06/16/eldiron-v0.8.4_rigging</link>
            <guid>https://eldiron.com/blog/2025/06/16/eldiron-v0.8.4_rigging</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 16 Jun 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[🎥 New Video is Live!]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="-new-video-is-live">🎥 New Video is Live!<a href="https://eldiron.com/blog/2025/06/16/eldiron-v0.8.4_rigging#-new-video-is-live" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 🎥 New Video is Live!" title="Direct link to 🎥 New Video is Live!">​</a></h2>
<p>🔥 <strong>Eldiron v0.84: Rigging</strong> is here — and it’s a game changer!</p>
<p>In this update, we introduce <strong>character rigging</strong> and <strong>equipment attachment</strong>, letting you build modular animated heroes with swords, shields, and more. Whether you’re designing a dungeon crawler or a retro RPG, this feature opens the door to dynamic, expressive characters.</p>
<iframe width="100%" height="400" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/d92Cl4qMFlc" title="Rigging" frameborder="0"></iframe>
<p>As always, thank you for your support. Your backing helps me push Eldiron further with every release!</p>
<p>—</p>
<p>Take care,
Markus</p>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>releases</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Eldiron v0.8.40 Released]]></title>
            <link>https://eldiron.com/blog/2025/06/13/eldiron-v0.8.40</link>
            <guid>https://eldiron.com/blog/2025/06/13/eldiron-v0.8.40</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 13 Jun 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Eldiron v0.8.40 Released]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="eldiron-v0840-released">Eldiron v0.8.40 Released<a href="https://eldiron.com/blog/2025/06/13/eldiron-v0.8.40#eldiron-v0840-released" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Eldiron v0.8.40 Released" title="Direct link to Eldiron v0.8.40 Released">​</a></h2>
<p>Eldiron v0.8.40 introduces a range of major new features for building retro-style RPGs:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p><strong>Character rigging and animation</strong>
Define and animate character rigs directly within the editor.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Item rigging and attachment</strong>
Equip characters with items that carry their own geometry and animation, attaching cleanly to character slots.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Terrain editing and procedural modification</strong>
Use sectors and linedefs combined with a node-based system to modify terrain heightmaps and colorization.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Node-based render graphs</strong>
All geometry in Eldiron—including characters, terrain, and items—is now driven by flexible, modular node graphs.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Asynchronous terrain and geometry streaming</strong>
Large environments now stream in and render smoothly in the background.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<video controls="" width="100%"><source src="/rigged_character.mov" type="video/quicktime"><p>Sorry, your browser doesn't support embedded videos.</p></video>
<p>Tutorial videos coming soon!</p>
<p>—</p>
<p>Take care,
Markus</p>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>releases</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[First Terrain Editing Screenshots]]></title>
            <link>https://eldiron.com/blog/2025/05/25/eldiron-terrain</link>
            <guid>https://eldiron.com/blog/2025/05/25/eldiron-terrain</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 25 May 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[As I work on the next release of Eldiron, I’ll post progress screenshots along the way. Here are two shots of the terrain modeling tools in action.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>As I work on the next release of Eldiron, I’ll post progress screenshots along the way. Here are two shots of the terrain modeling tools in action.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="Terrain Editing" src="https://eldiron.com/assets/images/terrainedit-e40ccad3c936211a60228f8592a19291.png" width="2624" height="1720" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>In the first screenshot, you can see how procedural nodes can be applied to sectors and linedefs to deform and colorize the terrain. For example, we flatten the ground and apply a stone texture, while the linedef creates a smooth path into the mountains.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="Terrain Editing" src="https://eldiron.com/assets/images/terrainbrushes-eb7ec294a0eecb510fa49d0639831c69.png" width="2624" height="1720" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>The second screenshot shows the new terrain tool, where we can sculpt the terrain using brushes. Rendering with terrain modifiers happens asynchronously in a background thread, providing a smooth and responsive editing experience.</p>
<p>—</p>
<p>Take care,
Markus</p>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>development update</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Eldiron Development Update 1]]></title>
            <link>https://eldiron.com/blog/2025/05/16/eldiron-devupdate</link>
            <guid>https://eldiron.com/blog/2025/05/16/eldiron-devupdate</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 16 May 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[As I’m working on the next release of Eldiron, I wanted to share a quick update on what’s happening behind the scenes. I originally planned to release new versions every 2–3 weeks, but this round is taking a bit longer—I’m deep in core systems that need to be just right before moving forward.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>As I’m working on the next release of Eldiron, I wanted to share a quick update on what’s happening behind the scenes. I originally planned to release new versions every 2–3 weeks, but this round is taking a bit longer—I’m deep in core systems that need to be just right before moving forward.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="render-graph">Render Graph<a href="https://eldiron.com/blog/2025/05/16/eldiron-devupdate#render-graph" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Render Graph" title="Direct link to Render Graph">​</a></h2>
<p>I’ve been integrating the new render graph system, which defines how the scene is drawn using a node-based approach. This allows plugging in effects like fog, ambient lighting, or even a fully procedural sky. More interestingly, this system ties directly into the map’s geometry—vertices, linedefs, and sectors.</p>
<p>You can now attach nodes directly to geometry to define local effects like lighting or fog, tweak terrain blending, or control glossiness and reflection on tiles. These graphs are reusable across multiple areas, making it easy to organize logic and effects in a modular way.</p>
<p>This isn't just visual fluff—eventually, these nodes will also drive gameplay interactions. Think of a node that defines a magical barrier, a trigger zone, or a destructible structure. The goal is to unify rendering, behavior, and logic into a single editable system.</p>
<p>And yes—this applies not just to 3D but also to 2D and isometric modes. The same systems work across all views, which keeps things consistent and flexible.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="terrain-system">Terrain System<a href="https://eldiron.com/blog/2025/05/16/eldiron-devupdate#terrain-system" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Terrain System" title="Direct link to Terrain System">​</a></h2>
<p>The new terrain tool lets you sculpt elevation with custom brushes—raise, lower, smooth, or roughen areas as you see fit. Tiles and materials blend automatically using rules, so you can paint smooth transitions and beautiful terrain with minimal effort.</p>
<p>All of this ties into the render graph too, which means terrain isn’t just a visual element—it can be procedural, dynamic, and reactive.</p>
<p>The inspiration is somewhere between “retro charming” and “early WoW Vanilla”—natural, stylized, and smooth, but still performant and easy to work with.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="asynchronous-streaming-terrain-and-geometry">Asynchronous Streaming Terrain and Geometry<a href="https://eldiron.com/blog/2025/05/16/eldiron-devupdate#asynchronous-streaming-terrain-and-geometry" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Asynchronous Streaming Terrain and Geometry" title="Direct link to Asynchronous Streaming Terrain and Geometry">​</a></h2>
<p>To support massive maps, terrain and geometry are now chunked and streamed in and out as needed. Unlike a game engine that only cares about the player’s position, Eldiron Creator has to update everything live as you edit.</p>
<p>That means background threads rebuild chunks, update render data, blend tiles, and apply node graphs without freezing the UI. It’s been a lot of low-level work, but it’s finally paying off—terrain edits feel smooth, and you can paint or modify geometry interactively.</p>
<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="whats-next">What’s Next<a href="https://eldiron.com/blog/2025/05/16/eldiron-devupdate#whats-next" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to What’s Next" title="Direct link to What’s Next">​</a></h2>
<p>I’m currently working on the first pass of procedural path nodes—letting you carve winding roads and trails that modify elevation and materials based on rules. These will connect with the graph system too, opening up possibilities for bridges, stairs, or terrain-aware gameplay triggers.</p>
<p>—</p>
<p>That’s it for now! Thanks again for following along—and for your support, especially on Patreon. The next version will be out once it’s stable and fun to use.</p>
<p>Take care,
Markus</p>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>development update</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Eldiron v0.8.23 Released — Procedural Materials!]]></title>
            <link>https://eldiron.com/blog/2025/04/24/eldiron-v0.8.23</link>
            <guid>https://eldiron.com/blog/2025/04/24/eldiron-v0.8.23</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 24 Apr 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Eldiron v0.8.23 is now available, introducing support for procedural materials.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><strong>Eldiron v0.8.23</strong> is now available, introducing support for procedural materials.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="Material" src="https://eldiron.com/assets/images/materials-82ef374a11621c7bdee715d85888d7ac.png" width="2624" height="1720" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>The new material system allows you to assign node-based effects to geometry, enabling tileable, unique materials for use in both 2D and 3D maps — fully integrated within Eldiron.</p>
<p>Current node types include color, distance-based gradients, and noise overlays. Additional nodes and advanced features will follow in upcoming releases.</p>
<p>You can now generate tiles directly from your maps, making Eldiron a fully self-sufficient game creation environment.</p>
<hr>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="new-in-v0823">New in v0.8.23<a href="https://eldiron.com/blog/2025/04/24/eldiron-v0.8.23#new-in-v0823" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to New in v0.8.23" title="Direct link to New in v0.8.23">​</a></h3>
<ul>
<li>Clipboard functionality for geometry (cut, copy, paste) in the map editor</li>
<li>Fog-based distance fading for 3D rendering</li>
<li>New region-based configuration system</li>
<li>Numerous fixes and general improvements</li>
</ul>
<hr>
<p>This release continues the path toward a complete retro RPG creation toolkit — more updates are coming soon.</p>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>releases</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Eldiron v0.8.22 Released]]></title>
            <link>https://eldiron.com/blog/2025/04/09/eldiron-v0.8.22</link>
            <guid>https://eldiron.com/blog/2025/04/09/eldiron-v0.8.22</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 09 Apr 2025 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Eldiron v0.8.22 is now available with several exciting new features and improvements.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Eldiron v0.8.22 is now available with several exciting new features and improvements.</p>
<h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="-whats-new">🆕 What's New<a href="https://eldiron.com/blog/2025/04/09/eldiron-v0.8.22#-whats-new" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 🆕 What's New" title="Direct link to 🆕 What's New">​</a></h3>
<ul>
<li><strong>Screens &amp; Widgets</strong> – Build your game's UI with buttons, text fields, message boxes, and more.</li>
<li><strong>New 2D Example: Hideout 2D</strong> – Explore a new demo where you help Moody the goblin re-unite with the treasures in his lair.</li>
</ul>
<p>I’ve created a new video walking through the new features and the Hideout 2D example. In it, I explain the mechanics behind characters, items, and the new UI system:</p>
<h2>Watch the Video</h2>
<iframe width="100%" height="400" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/mTZUf6c0xy4" title="Hideout 2D Example" frameborder="0"></iframe>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>releases</category>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>